Homage to the Buddha Shakyamuni.
Nam Mô Phật Bổn Sư Thích Ca Mâu
Greetings to all esteemed Dharma friends. Dear esteemed
Ni kính chào các quý Đạo Hữu Kính thưa
Dharma friends and Buddhist followers, many of you,
các quý đạo hữu nh phật tử của chúng ta
and many others with a similar mindset, used to
ấy và cũng là rất là nhiều người và tâm
think, "
nghĩ là thế này
How can I practice? I can't practice!"
này mình thì làm sao mà tu được mình
Many also held
không thể tu được đâu và cũng rất nhiều
the belief, "I
người có cái quan niệm là không Tôi
don't have the aptitude for practice. Only others have the aptitude for practice, not me.
không có căn tu cái người mới có căn tu
I don't have the aptitude,
chứ tôi không có căn tu tôi không có căn
so I can't practice."
tu cho nên là tu nó không được đâu Thế
So today, let's explore whether
thì hôm nay chúng ta đi tìm hiểu xem là
we can practice
chúng ta có tu được không Chúng ta có
or not. Let's find out if
căn tu hay không nhé để tìm hiểu xem
we have the aptitude for practice, and let's
mình có căn tu hay không và và chúng ta
also explore whether others have the aptitude for practice.
cũng tìm hiểu xem là người khác có căn
Practice
tu hay không thì chúng ta biết bởi vì Tu
is about ending suffering. Many people
là tu cho nó hết khổ có nhiều người thì
suffer, but when told to "just practice to
cũng khổ thế Nhưng bảo thôi tu đi cho nó
lessen the suffering," they say, "I don't have the aptitude for practice, so
bớt khổ thì bảo tôi không có căn tu cho
I can't." So today, let's
nên tôi không tu được thế thì hôm nay
identify whether we have the
chúng ta nhận diện xem mình là người có
aptitude for practice. Can we practice
căn tu không Mình có thể có khả năng tu
to end our own suffering? Can we attain
cho mình hết khổ được không Mình có thể
sainthood?
có khả năng tu thành thánh được hay
And what about others?  Whether or
không thế và người khác có căn tu hay
not someone has the potential to cultivate, and whether others can transform their
không người khác có thể tu mà chuyển
karma through practice, is crucial.
được nghiệp hay không vì Phật tử chúng
Buddhists often come to this place and ask, "
ta thường đến cái chỗ này chúng ta hỏi
This person
là thế này Cái người này là người ta
can't cultivate, can they?"
không tu được đâu thế và phật tử chúng
We also need to contemplate and
ta cũng rất cần cần cái sự quán chiếu
see if this person has the
xem là cái người này người ta có khả
potential to cultivate and transform their karma before
năng tu để chuyển nghiệp được không thì
we can guide them. This is very
chúng ta mới hướng dẫn cái đấy rất là
important, dear fellow practitioners.
quan trọng các quý đạo hữu ạ Thường
Often, we go to the marketplace for opportunities, and this
thường chúng ta đi chợ duyên mà nhà này
house encounters this problem, that house encounters that problem.
gặp việc này nhà kia gặp việc kia thế
We see people asking for our help,
phật tử chúng ta thấy người ta nhờ mình
but we don't
nhưng mà phật tử chúng ta cũng không
know how to
không không Cái biết biết cái cách là
assess whether this house has the potential to cultivate and
xem là nhà này người ta tu liệu người ta
whether they can transform their karma. We
có chuyển nghiệp được hay không Chúng ta
don't know, so sometimes we are
không biết cho nên đôi khi chúng ta mờ
confused, and our minds are still uncertain.
mịt thế cho nên tâm chếu hoàn Quán hôm
Today, I would like to share with you, dear fellow practitioners,
nay xin chia sẻ với các quý đạo hữu về
how to recognize whether you
cái cách nhận biết xem là mình Liệu mình
yourself can transform your karma through practice, and
tu có chuyển nghiệp được hay không và
how to recognize
cái cách nhận biết xem người khác người
if others have the potential to cultivate and
ta có căn tu hay không và người ta tu
whether they can transform their karma. Let's explore this through Sutta
không thì chúng ta tìm hiểu qua bài
171 in the Milinda Questions and Answers Sutta.  For
171 trong bộ kinh mi Tiên vấn đáp có tựa
those beings capable of attaining enlightenment, we respectfully
đề chúng sinh nào có khả năng đắc đạo
request that our esteemed fellow practitioners join
thì thỉnh các quý đạo hữ chúng ta Chắp
hands and recite the Buddha's name, seeking guidance and protection, so that
Tay Niệm hồng danh Phật cầu giáo hộ để
we may enter into this sharing session: Namo
chúng ta bước vào buổi chia
Buddha
Mô Phật
Shakyamuni, Namo
Thích Ca
Buddha Shakyamuni, Namo Buddha Shakyamuni.
Nam Mô Phật
Respectfully, esteemed fellow practitioners,
Ni à Kính thưa quý Đạo Hữu Tâm Chú Hoàn
please read the
quán xin Đọc văn
sutra. Reverend, all beings in
Kinh Thưa đại đức Tất cả chúng sinh bất
any realm, if they have pure faith,
cứ cõi nào nếu có đức tin trong sạch có
practice correctly and diligently,
sự thực hành chơ Chánh và tinh cần thì
can all attain sainthood. Venerable
thầy đều có thể Đắc thánh quả cả chứ đại
Nāgasena replied: There are those who can attain it, and there are those who
đức na-tiên đáp có loài có loại Đắc có
cannot. The king
loài có loại không thể đắc tâu đại vương
then asked: Respectfully, esteemed fellow practitioners, that is, King
thì Kính thưa quý đạo hữu tức là ông vua
Minanda. He asked: Is it true that all
minan đà ông hỏi là có phải là tất cả
beings in all realms—
chúng sinh trong tất cả các cõi này nào
heaven, humans, Asuras, and all
là trời người rồi A Tu La rồi tất cả các
realms of hell and hungry ghosts—that is, gods,
cõi địa ngục ngã quỷ tức là chư thiên
humans, hell, hungry ghosts, and animals—if they
loài người địa ngục ngã quỷ súc sinh nếu
practice correctly and diligently, and
như mà có sự thực hành chân chánh và
have faith in the Buddha's teachings, can
tinh cần có đức tin đối với phật pháp mà
all attain enlightenment? Venerable
thực hành như thế thì đều chứng Đắc được
Nāgasena replied: Yes, there are those who can.
thì đại đức na-tiên đáp là có loài chứng
There are beings who cannot attain enlightenment.
Đắc được có loài không chứng Đắc được ng
Please continue reading the
tâm chiếu Hoàn quán xin đọc tiếp Văn
scriptures. Which beings cannot attain enlightenment?
Kinh những chúng sinh nào không thể Đắc
Please tell me, Venerable Master. The king said
Xin Đại Đức kể cho nghe đức vua nói như
this, and Venerable Na Tien replied, "Your Majesty, there are
vậy đại đức Na tiên đáp tâu đại vương có
15 types of beings who cannot attain
15 loài Loại Chúng Sinh không thể đắc
the supreme fruit of enlightenment: animals and
đạo quả cao siêu được đó là súc vật cầm
beasts; two types of sentient beings;
thú hai loài khẩn naana chúng sinh Phi
flying creatures with human-like heads (like
mà lửa thú mại mang cái hình đầu giống
monkeys, for
đầu người đấy giống như là cái con khỉ
example; their heads are very similar to
chẳng hạn cái đầu nó cũng rất là giống
human heads, but their bodies
đầu người nhưng cái thân bên dưới của nó
are animal-like; or the body of a creature with an inverted head, right?
là à thân của loài thú hoặc là cái con
But their bodies are animal-like;
nhưng thân của nó thì lại mang thân thú
three are dragons; four are hungry ghosts; five are
ba là loài rồng bốn là ngã quỷ năm là
people with wrong views (people with wrong views are those who
người tà kiến thì cái người tà kiến là
do not believe in karma, who do not believe in
mà không tin vào nhân quả không tin vào
the path to enlightenment and liberation that the
con đường mà giác ngộ giải thoát mà Đức
Buddha spoke of). All of these people
Phật nói ra thì tất cả những người đó
are called people with wrong views,
chúng ta đều được gọi là người tà kiến
lacking right views. And what about
đấy không có chính kiến Thế còn cái
people who believe in karma? Those who believe
người người mà tin vào nhân quả đấy Cái
in the Four Noble Truths?  A
người tin được về Tứ Diệu Đế Tức là cái
person who recognizes the suffering of
người là nhận diện các cái việc của thế
this world and
gian thế này là khổ và cái người tin
believes that all the suffering in
được rằng tất cả những cái khổ của thế
this world is caused by
gian này Nguyên nhân là do chính là tham
craving. For example, we suffer from the suffering
ái ví dụ chúng ta chịu những cái khổ là
of birth, old age, sickness, and
cái khổ của sinh của già của bệnh của
death; the suffering of unfulfilled desires; the suffering of being separated from
chết cái khổ của cầu mong muốn không
loved ones; the suffering of being
của yêu nhau mà lại phải xa cách
together with enemies; the suffering of the Five Aggregates (form, feeling, perception, volition, and consciousness).
phải hội tụ với nhau cái khổ của cái Ngũ
All
này nó làm cho chúng ta khổ thì tất cả
this suffering is caused by
cái khổ đó là do cái tâm tham của chúng
our greed;
ta nó khiến cho chúng ta bị cái khổ đó
it is our craving that causes
nó do cái tâm Ái của chúng ta khiến cho
us suffering.
chúng ta bị cái khổ đó gọi là nguyên
A person who understands
đấy thì cái người mà như hiểu biết như
this is called a person with right
vậy gọi là người có chính
view. They know that eliminating greed and
kiến biết được rằng là diệt cái tâm tham
craving will end suffering. A
đi diệt cái tâm ái thì hết khổ thì cái
person
người đó gọi là người có chính kiến còn
who thinks that suffering is caused by
cái người mà lại nghĩ rằng là do ông
God, that the gods
trời khiến tôi phải khổ do các ngài
do not protect them, is called a person with wrong
không phù hộ cho tôi cho nên tôi phải
view.  Both
khổ cái đấy gọi là t tả kiến và tất cả
those so-called supernatural powers that
những cái gọi là năng lực siêu nhiên nào
cause suffering and those that
đó khiến cho mình phải khổ và từ một cái
bring
năng lực siêu nhiên nào đó khiến cho
happiness and peace are
mình được hạnh phúc an lành Thì cái đấy
called wrong views.
gọi là tà
Many other wrong views cling to permanence and annihilation.
kiến rồi Nhiều cái tà kiến khác chấp
Sixth, children
thường chấp đoạn nhiều lắm sáu là trẻ
under 7 years old. That is, those under 7 years old
chưa đủ 7 tuổi Tức là cái người chưa đủ
cannot attain
7 tuổi thì chưa thể Đắc được thánh
sainthood. Eighth, those who commit patricide. Ninth, those who commit
quả tám là người phạm tội giết cha chín
mother murder. Those who commit the crime of
là người phạm tội giết mẹ người là phạm
killing an Arhat. Respectfully, dear fellow
tội giết A la hán đây Kính thưa quý đạo
practitioners, there are also those who
hữu cũng có những cái người người ta
commit the crime of killing an Arhat because
phạm tội giết A la hán được vì là thân
their bodies are made of the four elements, and
của các ngài là thân tứ đại thế thì các
they are very free to enter Nirvana. But
ngài rất là tự tại nhập diệt thế nhưng
because of
mà do cái cái cái cái cái cái cái cái
someone who harms their bodies,
người nào đó mà hại cái thân tứ đại của
because of that cause, they die, and
các ngài vì cái nhân duyên đó các ngài
that person
nhật diệt thì cái người đó cũng không
cannot cultivate or attain enlightenment,
thể tu đắc được không thể tu đắc đạo
even if they repent and practice the
được dù là sau đó sám hối rồi vào trong
Buddha's teachings. That is,
giáo pháp của Phật tu thì cũng không thể
those who kill their father,
đắc đạo được Tức là người giết cha giết
mother, or Arhat, those who draw the Buddha's blood (making the
mẹ giết A la hán kẻ chích máu Phật tức
Buddha's body bleed),
là làm cho thân Phật ch chảy máu đấy
those who cause division within the Sangha... Respectfully, dear fellow
người chia rẽ tăng thì Kính thưa các quý
practitioners.  There are people who sow discord among the Sangha, and
đạo hữu cái người chia rẽ tăng này phật
we Buddhists must be aware of this because it's very easy to
tử chúng ta phải phải lưu ý vì rất là dễ
sow discord within the Sangha. This can happen when a monk speaks
chia rẽ tăng đến cái chỗ vị tăng này nói
falsely about other monks,
sai sự thật về về cái vị Chư tăng kia
causing division within the
làm cho người ta chia rẽ nhau chia rẽ
Sangha. For example, the Sangha
tăng đoàn ví dụ như là tăng đoàn chúa
is a pure and virtuous community,
vàng là tăng đoàn tu tập thanh tịnh như
but then someone says that
thế thế nhưng mà lại nói ra rằng là tăng
some members are
đoàn những người này là những người
not practitioners, that they are fake, that they practice this way, that they
không phải là người tu người này là giả
are
Tu người này là thế này Người này là thế
that way, causing division within the
kia làm cho tăng đoàn bị chia rẽ tăng
Sangha and among sentient beings, making
đoàn với lại chúng sinh khiến cho người
people lose faith in the Sangha. This is
ta không tin vào tăng đoàn nữa thì đấy
called sowing discord within the Sangha, or
gọi là người chia rẽ Chia rẽ tăng hoặc
so it is, causing division within the Sangha, preventing the Sangha from being
tức là chia cứ chia rẽ tăng làm cho tăng
close to the Four Assemblies, and leading
không gần được với Tứ chúng làm cho vị
other monks to misunderstand the
tăng khác hiểu sai vị tăng này hiểu sai
truth. Speaking the truth is fine.
sự thật đi còn nói sự thật thì không sao
Sowing discord within the Sangha refers to saying
nhá Đây Chia rẽ tăng là thuộc về nói
things that cause misunderstandings and misinterpretations of the
những lời khiến cho người ta hiểu lầm
Sangha. If one understands the truth, it is
tăng hiểu không đúng sự thật về chưa
not considered sowing discord within the
tăng còn hiểu đúng sự thật thì không
Sangha. For example, saying that the monk who
phải chia rẽ tăng đoàn ví dụ như là ông
harmed the Buddha is the one who caused the Sangha to be divided.
để bà đặt Đa ông ấy là người hại Phật
The Buddha said...  If someone says that
thế thì Đức Phật có nói là ông để bà Đạt
Bodhidharma harmed the Buddha, then that statement is
Đa là người hại Phật thì cứ câu nói đó
not about dividing the Sangha. If we
không phải là chia rẽ tăng và chúng ta
say that Bodhidharma harmed the Buddha, it's
nói rằng đề bà Đạt Đa là người hại Phật
not about dividing the Sangha. Similarly, if a monk has wrong
thì không phải là người chia dẽ tăng
views,
hoặc một vị Chư tăng nào đó có tà kiến
and we say that monk has
mà chúng ta nói rằng cái vị tăng đó có
wrong views, it's not about dividing the Sangha.
tà kiến thì không phải là chia rẽ tăng
Many people don't understand what "
nhiều người không không hiểu về thế nào
dividing the Sangha" means, so they don't dare speak out about
là chia rẽ tăng cho nên là Chư tăng có
the many mistakes monks make that harm sentient beings. They
lỗi rất nhiều làm hại chúng sinh rất
say they're afraid to say it because they're afraid of committing the sin of
nhiều không dám nói ra nói là tôi sợ nói
dividing the Sangha. This
như thế là mắc vào tội chia sẽ tăng đây
is due to a lack of knowledge. However, if
là do không có kiến thức Còn nếu Chư
that monk truly harmed the
tăng đó quả thật là cái người làm hại
Buddha's teachings and preached wrong views,
Phật Pháp là cái người giảng thuyết tà
then we must tell everyone so they
kiến thì chúng ta phải nói cho mọi người
don't follow
biết để cho mọi người không đi theo cái
those wrong doctrines. Then we won't be
sự tà thuyết đó nữa thì chúng ta không
committing the sin of dividing the Sangha;
phải là mắc vào cái tội chia rẽ tăng mà
we'll be protecting the Buddha's teachings. But
chúng ta gọi là bảo vệ Phật pháp Nhưng
we must know the truth
chúng ta phải biết như chân như thật
clearly, not speak falsely. If we don't know clearly
biết rõ chứ không phải là không biết rõ
and speak falsely, then
không biết rõ mà nói sai sự thật thì
we'll also be committing this sin.
chúng ta cũng mắc vào cái tội này nhá
Therefore, we see that those who
Thế cho nên là chúng ta thấy này người
divide the Sangha are those who practice Buddhism.  If you ca
chia dĩa tăng là cái người có tu cũng
n't attain enlightenment by speaking falsely about
không đắc đạo được nói sai sự thật về
monks, even if you practice, you won't
Chư tăng thì có tu cũng không đắc đạo
attain enlightenment. For example, if someone says
được Chư tăng này như thế này nhưng nói
something false about a monk, even if they
sai sự thật về cái Chư tăng đó thì cái
practice, they will never attain enlightenment. For instance, if
người này có tu cũng không bao giờ đắc
someone says a monk isn't a
đạo được đấy ví dụ chữ tăng này người ta
fraud, and
không phải là người lừa đảo lại nói chữ
that monk isn't a
tăng này là là người lừa đảo thì cái
fraud,
người nào đã vị Chư tăng nào đã nói như
then that monk will
thế thì cái vị Chư tăng đó ngay trong
never attain enlightenment in this lifetime. (Regarding
đời này không bao giờ tu đắc đạo được n
the story
tâm chiếu Hoàn quán chia sẻ cái chuyện
of our temple, I'm sharing this about the incident with the
của chùa chúng ta đó là cái đợt vụ báo
Labor Newspaper. When the newspaper wrote that
lao động khi báo viết là ví dụ như
our monks were a source of
là Chư tăng của chùa chúng ta là nguồn
hundreds of billions of dong in revenue, they put a
thu trăm tỷ nhưng họ lại nói là có dấu
question mark in the text. They wrote it as a question mark, meaning they were
hỏi họ viết là dấu hỏi tức là họ hỏi
questioning whether it was true
chấm Đúng không là nghi vấn có phải thế
or not. But then there was a
hay không không thế nhưng mà cũng có vị
monk who spoke loudly, saying that
Chư tăng thì lại nói sưng sưng lên là sư
our master and the monks were fraudsters and deceivers,
phụ của chúng ta và Chư tăng là lừa đảo
while the newspaper
là mị dân mà trong khi đó báo thì người
only used a question mark. Yet
ta lại chỉ đánh dấ hỏi thôi Thế nhưng vị
that monk spoke
Chư tăng kia thì lại nói nói xưng sưng
loudly, saying it was the truth, and even saying it was a lie.)
lên nói là sự thật lại còn nói là vi
Violating this criminal law,
phạm vào điều luật hình sự này vi phạm
violating that criminal law, while the news
vào điều luật hình sự kia trong khi đó
report is just a hypothesis, the truth is
báo mới là giả thiết thế còn sự thật thì
not like that. Therefore, after
không phải là như thế cho nên là sau cái
that news report,
vụ báo nói đấy thì
our temple did not seem to have committed
chùa chúng ta không thấy bị mắc phải cái
any crime. So, the monk who said that
tội gì cả Thế thì cái vị Chư tăng nói
committed the karmic act of
như vậy là mắc vào cái nhân duyên là
dividing the Sangha from the Fourfold Assembly, and such a
người chia rẽ tăng với Tứ chúng thì cái
person will never attain enlightenment in this life.
người này tu trong đời này không bao giờ
We affirm this
đắc đạo được đấy là chúng ta khẳng định
from this sutra, so we know
từ cái bài kinh này nên chúng ta biết
that. Many monks in the
điều đó và nhiều vị Chư tăng trong cái
labor newspaper also committed
việc báo lao động cũng mắc vào cái tội
this crime of speaking falsely, so the crime of speaking
này nói sai sự thật cho nên cái tội nói
falsely is the crime of dividing the Sangha. Therefore,
sai sự thật đó là cái tội chia rẽ tăng
those who have spoken like that will
thế thì những cái vị đã nói như vậy
not attain enlightenment in this life.
trong đời này cũng không tu đắc đạo Được
So we must be very careful about
đấy cho nên chúng ta rất là cẩn thận về
what we say about the monks. We must know and
cái việc nói về Chư tăng là phải biết rõ
understand
hiểu
clearly before we speak the truth.
rõ chúng ta mới được nói lên cái sự thật
We shouldn't lose our vigilance and
đó chứ không phải là chúng ta mất tỉnh
say things that are untrue because of some
không lành mà chúng ta nói ra những cái
impure intention. We are harming ourselves, are
điều sai sự thật thì chúng ta hại chính
n't we, dear fellow practitioners? We are
chúng ta phải không quý đạo hữu chúng ta
harming the Sangha.
hại chính chúng ta tâm chiếu Hoàn quán
Please
xin đọc
continue reading, my mind is focused on the path of enlightenment. A person who steals the monastic robe
tiếp Người phạm giới trộm tăng tướng
or impersonates a monk, or a bhikkhu who follows a heterodox path,
hoặc à tỳ Khưu hành theo ngoại đạo Người
is
phạm giới trộm mạo tăng tướng Tức là cái
someone who has not received the monastic robes
người không được thọ giới tăng không
but has not been ordained by a teacher. If they
được thầy thế phát cho mình mà tự mình
shave their head and wear the robe themselves,
cạo tóc tự mình mặc y cà sa thì cái
that person is called a thief of the monastic robe,
người đó gọi là trộm tướng
and they cannot attain enlightenment.
tăng thì cái người đó cũng không tu đắc
Respectfully, dear fellow
được Kính thưa quý đạo hữu như là vị cư
practitioners, if a layperson attains Arhatship, on
sĩ mà tu đắc quả A La Hán Thì ngày hôm
that day they must seek out a teacher,
đó cũng phải đi tìm đến các cái vị thầy
even if that teacher has not yet attained enlightenment. A
dù vị thầy đó là vị thầy chưa Đắc quả
teacher who has the legitimate appearance of a monk, in accordance with the teachings, can still shave the head of the
lý người ta xuống tóc cho cái vị cư sĩ
layperson who has attained Arhatship.
đã đã Đắc quả A La Hán kia người ta vẫn
Because of the
xuống tóc được cơ mà Tại vì trong cái
layperson's physical form, they can
thân tướng cư sĩ Thế cho nên người ta
still shave their head. After shaving their head,
vẫn xuống tóc được và xuống tóc xong thì
that layperson becomes an Arhat and
vị cư sĩ đó là thành vị tăng A La Hán và
will maintain their life,
sẽ duy trì cái mạng sống cái thân tứ đại
this physical body, in this human realm. However,
này ở ở tại cái cõi người này Thế còn
if that layperson cannot find a
nếu như mà cái vị cư sĩ đó không tìm
teacher to shave their head, then
được vị thầy mà xuống tóc cho mình thì
that layperson will enter Nirvana. But Nirvana
vị cư sĩ đó nhập diệt Nhưng mà nhập diệt
with  The merit is that of an Arhat.
với cái cái Phúc quả là A la hán nhá Thế
So here we see that a person
thì ở đây chúng ta thấy rằng cái người
who has committed a crime, who has violated the precept of stealing and impersonating a
mà đã phạm tội đã phạm vào cái giới trộm
monk, will
mạo tăng tướng thì cái người này trong
not attain enlightenment in this life. Even if they become monks, they will
đời này cũng không tu đắc quả được có đi
not attain enlightenment. That is
xuất gia cũng thật cũng không tu đắc quả
another cause:
được đấy Đấy là nhân duyên thứ nữa là
or if a monk follows external doctrines, then,
hoặc tỳ Khưu hành theo ngoại Đạ thì Kính
dear fellow practitioners, I, the Mind-Viewing
thưa quý đạo hữu chỗ này thì tâm chiếu
Enlightenment, will share this widely so that you
Hoàn quán cũng chia sẻ rộng cho quý đạo
understand that there are some monks who have
hữu chúng ta hiểu có những vị thầy đi
become monks and taken vows under the Buddhist precepts,
xuất gia rồi Thọ dưới nhà phật rồi thế
but then go into spirit mediumship—
nhưng lại đi hầu
that is, they follow the practices of external doctrines. Then they also go into fortune-telling, physiognomy, and
thế rồi lại còn đi xem bói đấy xem bói
feng shui.
xem tướng Xem phong thủy đấy thì những
These people will not attain enlightenment in this life.
cái vị này trong đời này cũng không tu
This is in
đắc đạo được đấy Đây là trong bài kinh
this sutra. The Mind-Viewing Enlightenment continues: Those who
này Đấy tâm chếu hoàn quán đọc tiếp kẻ
rape nuns or monks who commit monastic transgressions
hãm hiếp tỳ kheo ni hoặc tỳ Khưu phạm
and do not receive punishment—
tăng tàn mà không Thọ lãnh hình phạt thì
that is, those who, before
tức là những người mà khi chưa xuất gia
or after becoming monks, raped nuns—
hoặc đã xuất gia mà hãm hiếp tỳ kheo ni
these people, even if they practice in this life, will
thì những người này trong cuộc đời này
not attain enlightenment. And
họ có tu đi chăng nữa cũng không đắc đạo
those monks who have taken vows
được và những hàng tỳ kheo đã thọ giớii
but commit such transgressions...  To violate the monastic precepts without
rồi mà phạm t phạm vào tăng tàn mà không
receiving punishment means not receiving the
Thọ lãnh hình phạt Tức là không Thọ lãnh
precepts prescribed by the Dharma teachings.
những cái cái cái cái cái pháp học đưa
After violating these precepts,
ra sau khi đã phạm vào giưới này thì
such a person cannot attain enlightenment. We are not
người này cũng không đắc đạo được thì
monks, so
không phải là người xuất gia cho nên
we won't discuss the monastic precepts.
chúng ta không bàn
In all 250 precepts for monks, whoever
đến trong tất cả h 250 giới dành cho tỳ
violates a precept
kheo tăng thì ai phạm vào giới nào thì
has a specific way of repenting for that precept.
đều có cái cách Sám Hối của giới đó Thế
Here, we are talking about someone who violates the monastic precepts.
ở đây thì nói về cái người phạm giới là
If they do not repent
phạm vào tăng tàn nếu như không sám hối
and do not practice the
và không thực hành theo những cái điều
prescribed methods to transform the karmic
quy định tức là thực hành để chuyển hóa
consequences,
nhân quả ấy mà tức là Chư tăng phạm giới
then the monks who violate the precepts have ways to practice Dharma
thì Chư tăng lại có cách thực hành pháp
to transform the karmic consequences caused by that violation. It's like when
để chuyển hóa cái Nhân Quả do Phạm giới
we smear black marks on our face,
chúng ta bôi cái vết đen vào mặt thì
we have a way to
chúng ta phải có cách là chúng ta lấy
wash them off with a cloth. The
khăn chúng ta rửa đi thì nó hết thế thì
monks are the same; they have received 250 precepts, and
chư T cũng thế các ngài Thọ 250 giới rồi
if they violate any precept, they
thế nếu các ngài phạm vào giới nào thì
have ways to practice Dharma to
các ngài lại có cách thực hành pháp để
transform the karmic consequences of
các ngài chuyển hóa hết cái nhân quả của
that precept.  So that you can become
cái giới đó đi để cho các vị lại trở nên
pure again, then you can continue to
thanh tịnh rồi các vị lại tiếp tục tu
practice and sow seeds of merit. It's not that breaking the
tập và rắc quả được Thế chứ không phải
precepts means there's no
là cứ phạm giới cái là không còn cơ hội
more opportunity. These 25 precepts all have ways
nữa đâu 25 m giới này đều có cái cách mà
to practice and transform the cause and
để tu tập để chuyển hóa cái nhân nhân
effect. So just keep diligently practicing, with a pure and contemplative
quả đi được thế cho nên là cứ tinh tấn
mind. Please continue reading about
tu thôi tâm chếu hoàn quán xin đọc tiếp
the male and female sellers, and the
người bán Nam bán nữ và người cái hạng
last category of people: those with two sets of
người cuối cùng đó là người có hai xanh
genitalia, meaning those with two sets of
thực khí tức là người có hai bộ phận
reproductive organs. We also see some children with one upper body but two lower bodies, meaning four sets of genitalia. There are also
có hai cái bộ phận sinh dục thì cũng có
children with two heads,
những cái đứa trẻ thì nó có hai phần đầu
or children whose
hay có đứa trẻ thì lại dính nhau ấy dính
genitalia are fused together,
nhau thì lại có hai bộ phận sinh dục là
fused from the feet down, but only one
dính từ chân dính xuống nhưng chỉ có một
head. People like
phần đầu thôi thì những cái người mà như
that cannot attain enlightenment.
thế cũng không thể tu đắc đạo được thế
Respectfully, dear friends, here we will
Kính thưa quý đảo Hữu ở đây chúng ta sẽ
have a perspective that these people
có cái cách nhìn tức là những người này
cannot
thì mới không tu đắc đạo Tức là không
attain enlightenment. That is, they cannot transform their
đắc đạo Tức là không chuyển được nghiệp
karma.  While it's impossible to become a saint without
từ Phàm thành thành thánh được không
transforming our karma, these fifteen types of beings
chuyển được còn 15 loài loại chúng sinh
can all cultivate and transform their karma, and
này thì đều có thể tu Chuyển Nghiệp được
can all become saints. So let's
đều có thể Tu thành thánh được đấy Thế
examine ourselves:
chúng ta thì tự xét chúng ta này Thứ
Firstly, we are human beings,
nhất là chúng ta đang là thân người loại
not animals or beasts. Secondly,
cái đầu tiên là súc vật cầm thú là không
we are not the kind of creatures that hide behind human heads,
sinh Phi cầm có đầu giấu người thì chúng
nor are we the kind of beings that
ta cũng không phải thế và cái người mà
we see.
chúng ta đến xem cũng không phải thế thứ
Furthermore, we are not dragons, nor are we
nữa là loài rồng thì chúng ta cũng không
evil spirits, nor are we
phải ngã quỷ chúng ta cũng không phải
people with wrong views, nor
người tà kiến chúng ta cũng không
are we children under seven years old; we are
phải trẻ chưa đủ 7 tuổi thì chúng ta
over seven years old.
cũng không phải chúng ta trên 7 tuổi rồi
Those who commit patricide are not guilty of murder, nor
Người phạm vào tội giết cha thì không
are those who kill their mothers, nor are those who kill
phải tội giết mẹ thì không phải giết A
Arhats, nor are those who bleed Buddhas. The
la hán thì không phải kẻ chích máu Phật
main thing is to
thì không phải chủ yếu là chúng ta phải
observe whether we have committed the
quan sát xem đây là chúng ta có bị vào
sin of causing division within the Sangha.
cái tội chia rẽ tăng không thôi Cái chia
This division within the Sangha is extremely important because
rẽ tăng này là vô cùng quan trọng vì
we must examine ourselves to see if we have
chúng ta phải tự xem xem là chúng ta có
ever slandered the monks, or
đi vu khống cho Chư tăng bao giờ chưa
spread
đúng không vu khống cho họ nói cho nhiều
falsehoods about them to many people.  Is it true
người biết nói sai sự thật về họ để cho
that someone who has distanced themselves from the Sangha, or who has slandered the Sangha, is not necessarily
là người khác xa rời Chư tăng hay không
someone who has committed false accusations? If you haven't slandered them, then you can still attain enlightenment. And if someone has violated the precepts,
thể tu đắc đạo được và người có phạm
stolen from or impersonated a monk, or practiced
giới trộm mạo tăng tướng hoặc tỳ kheo
heterodox teachings, then you are not
hành ngoại đạo hay không thì mình không
necessarily someone who rapes a nun
phải như thế thứ nữa là kẻ hãm hiếp tỳ
or a monk who commits a
kheo ni hoặc tỳ kheo phạm tăng tàn mà
serious offense without receiving punishment, then you are
không Thọ lạnh hình phạt thì mình cũng
not necessarily someone who sells men or
không phải thế thứ nữa là người bán Nam
women, or someone who has
bán nữ mình cũng không phải thế người có
two genitals, then you are not
hai xanh thực khí thì mình cũng không
necessarily someone who has two genitals. And you should also examine the
phải thế và mình cũng quán xét như thế
person you are facing—the
đối với người đối diện mình những cái
person they are talking to—
người mà họ họ họ họ họ nói chuyện với
in this way. If they say, "I have no foundation for cultivation," then you just need to ask them, "Have you ever divided the Sangha? Have you ever slandered or falsely accused the Sangha?" As for
khống cho Chư tăng chưa thôi còn các cái
these things, whether you have wrong views
này thì mới lại bạn có là người tà kiến
or not doesn't matter. Now, just
hay không tà kiến thì không sao bây giờ
return to the observation that enlightenment is
quay trở lại chứng kiến là được giác ngộ
attainable. That is, you just need to
là được thế tức là mình Bây giờ chỉ cần
ask them, "Have you ever divided the Sangha? Have you ever slandered or falsely accused the Sangha?" That's all.  If
hỏi người ta đã từng chia rẽ tăng đoàn
someone says
thế thôi thế Nếu người họ bảo là họ chưa
they haven't done it yet, then we know they
họ chưa làm điều đó thì mình biết là họ
have the potential to attain enlightenment. But for
có khả năng tu đạt đạo được thế còn đối
lay people, if they are accused of speaking
với hàng cư sĩ Nếu mà vào cái bị là nói
ill of monks and causing division within the monastic community, then
xấu Chư tăng chia rẽ tăng đoàn Thì bây
they must go to the monks and
giờ mình phải đến Chư tăng mình sám hối
repent. Even if they don't attain
mình sám hối thì tuy rằng mình không tu
enlightenment, they can still
đắc quả được nhưng mình tu vẫn sao
transform their karma. That person can
chuyển nghiệp được thì cái người đó tu
still transform their karma; they
vẫn chuyển nghiệp được có cái là không
just won't become a saint or enter the lineage of
thành thánh được thôi không vào dòng
saints, but they can still transform the karma that causes them
thánh được thôi nhưng vẫn chuyển nghiệp
suffering. They
được những cái nghiệp mà đang chịu khổ
just won't
là vẫn chuyển được Chỉ có cái là không
attain sainthood. So here, I, with a clear
vào quả thánh được thôi cho nên ở đây
mind and a contemplative perspective, would like to share with you all that
tâm chiếu Hoàn quán xin chia sẻ với các
if we go to someone's house and
quý đạo hữu nếu như chúng ta đến một nhà
sow seeds of merit, and
nào đó chúng ta gieo duyên thì chúng ta
say, "I'm not sure if my family's karma
cũng người ta mà nói rằng là nhà tôi tu
can be transformed,"
không biết có chuyển nghiệp hay không
we can show
thì chúng ta đưa ra 15 cái cái cái cái
them these 15 things and say, "If you don't have
cái cái này cho họ xem bảo nếu không mắc
these 15 things, you can transform your
phải 15 n cái này thì có thể tu Chuyển
karma." Now, all you need to do is take refuge in the
Nghiệp được Bây giờ chỉ cần là đi quy y
Three Jewels, study the Dharma, and cultivate right views to
Tam Bảo tu học Phật pháp để tăng trưng
transform your karma, right?
Chính kiến là sẽ chuyển nghiệp đúng
If you have ever caused division within the monastic community...  If
không Nếu như mà đã từng chia rẽ tăng
the group speaks ill of the monks, then go to the monks' place to
đoàn nói xấu Chư tăng thì về nơi Chư
repent. If we practice, we can
tăng sám hối thì mình tu thì mình có thể
transform our karma, and
chuyển hóa được nghiệp của mình và tự
everyone will check for themselves whether they have
người sẽ kiểm tra xem là mình có mắc vào
dual sexual desires. If
là có hai sinh dục hay không Nếu không
not, then we can practice. So, through
có thì tu được nhá Cho nên qua cái phần
this sharing, I, Hoan Quan, have
chia sẻ này tâm chứ Hoàn quán cũng cũng
learned more, and our fellow practitioners have
học thêm được và các quý đạo hữu chúng
also learned more to be confident when
ta cũng học thêm được để mạnh dạn khi đi
sharing Buddhist teachings and encouraging people to
chia sẻ phật pháp và khuyến tấn người ta
diligently practice to transform their
tinh tấn thực hành để mà chuyển hóa
karma. Having the right conditions
nghiệp lực đấy có đầy đủ cái nhân duyên
like this is enough to transform
như này là có thể chuyển hóa được nghiệp
karma, and we can also answer
lực và chúng ta cũng trả lời với mọi
people when they say, "I don't have the
người khi họ nói rằng là tôi không có
potential to practice,"
căn tu
knowing that everyone has the potential to practice.
và chúng ta biết rằng ai cũng có căn tu
If we get past 10 years of this kind of thing...
Nếu mà ra khỏi 10 năm cái loại này thế
Actually, we only consider about 14 or
Thực ra chúng ta chỉ tính đến khoảng 14
13 because with wrong views, we build up
13 thôi vì tà kiến thì chúng ta xây dựng
our understanding through listening and learning to develop right
cho chúng ta nghe học là thành có chính
views. Because here we talk about attaining enlightenment,
kiến thôi Tại vì ở đây nói là đắc đạo
meaning no one can attain
Tức là không ai có thể tả kiến mà lại
enlightenment with wrong views; one must have right views to
đắc đạo được cả thế phải có chính kiến
attain enlightenment. As for those
thì mới đắc đạo được thế còn những người
below, who follow heterodox teachings...  It's
bên dưới này thì Khưu hành theo ngoại
true that they haven't attained enlightenment. So
đạo thì không đắc đạo là đúng rồi Thế
now, if this monk wants to
giờ cái muốn cái vị t cưu này mà muốn
attain enlightenment, he must repent, take the
đắc đạo được thì phải sám hối lại phải
precepts again, right? He must take the precepts again and practice
thọ giới lại đúng không thọ giới lại tu
again to attain enlightenment. Otherwise, he
lại thì mới đắc đạo được chứ nếu không
cannot attain enlightenment. As for the person who
thì không đắc đạo được còn cái người
caused the division of the Sangha, that's a very serious sin, so I do
chia rẽ tăng này thì nó vào tội rất lớn
n't know if they can attain it or
được thì không biết là cái tỳ Khưu hành
not.
giới lại tu thì có đắc được hay không TH
Furthermore, Master La Tien said there are 15 types of beings who cannot attain high enlightenment. I don't know if this monk who followed an external religion, if he repents and takes the precepts again, will attain it. However, there are also sins
thế nhưng mà nhưng mà còn những cái tội
like killing an Arhat, drawing the Buddha's blood,
mà phạm tội giết A la hán trích máu Phật
killing one's father or mother—
à tội giết cha giết mẹ những cái tội
these sins definitely prevent one from attaining
trên là khẳng định không Đắc được A La
Arhatship in this life. So, regarding these
Hán trong đời này rồi thế thì còn đây
related matters, I do
những cái điều tương ưng thì mình cũng
n't know yet, so I
chưa thể mình chưa biết cho nên mình
dare not say for sure whether this monk who
không dám nói chắc là cái người đã hành
followed an external religion, if he
theo tỳ Khưu hành theo ngoại đạo này sám
repents and practices again, can attain enlightenment. I would
hối rồi tu tập lại có thể đắc đạo được
n't say that because this is
mình cũng không nói thế Vì cái này nó
different from the
lại không giống trường hợp ở bên trên
case above, where the person committed the sin of
trường hợp ở bên trên là người phạm tội
killing their father or mother.
giết cha giết mẹ
Children under the age of 7 – that's a
người trẻ chưa đủ 7 tuổi đấy là Điều
definite fact, a definite fact.  It's
khẳng định luôn đấy khẳng định chứ ở đây
not said here that someone who followed a
không nói là người này đã hành theo
heterodox path must repent to attain enlightenment. It's
ngoại đạo thì phải sám hối mới đắc đạo ở
not said that way, so we ca
đây không nói thế cho nên chúng ta cũng
n't say that either. We only know
không nói như thế được chúng ta chỉ biết
that someone who followed a heterodox
là người hành theo ngoại
path, even after receiving the Bhikkhu ordination, will
đạo khi đã thọ giới tỳ kheo thì là người
not attain enlightenment according to the scriptures.
không đắc đạo đúng theo kinh văn
T. Chi Hoan Quan, please continue reading: 10
thôi à T chế Hoàn quán xin đọc tiếp 10
years of this type of being, even with
năm hạng chúng sinh này dù đức tin trong
pure faith and righteous practice, diligently cultivating tranquility and insight,
sạch thực hành chân chánh Tiến tu chỉ
cannot enter the lineage of the
tịnh quán Minh cũng không thể vào dòng
saints. Respectfully, dear fellow practitioners,
thánh chủng được th Kính thưa quý đạo
this is confirmed. 15 types of
hữu cái này thì khẳng định rồi ạ 15 Loại
beings, even those who, as
Chúng Sinh này thì kể cả là cái người mà
Bhikkhus, followed a heterodox path, even with
tỳ Khưu hành theo ngoại đạo dù là đã đầy
complete pure faith and righteous practice, diligently cultivating tranquility and insight,
đủ đức tin trong sạch thực hành chân
cannot enter the lineage of the saints. It's
không thể vào dọng dòng thánh trùng được
very dangerous. That is, even if they see
rất là nguy hiểm tức là họ có thấy họ
their mistakes, turn back, repent, and
sai họ có quay trở lại họ có sám hối họ
practice, they cannot enter. The same applies to
có tu tập cũng không thể vào được và cái
those who cause division
người chia rẽ tăng cũng thế Có sám hối
within the Sangha. Even if they repent, regain their true faith, and diligently practice meditation, they
rồi có lại được cái đức tin trong chân
cannot enter the lineage of fruition. This is a
cũng không vào dòng quả được đây là câu
confirmation from the holy Arhat
khẳng định của ngài thánh Tăng A la hán
Na Tien.  King Mindā nodded. "I have
Na tiên nhé đức vua Min đà gật đầu Trẫm
no doubt about that, I only
không hề nghi ngờ về điều ấy chỉ thắc
have one small question, Your Majesty.
mắc một điểm nhỏ
Please feel free to
thôi đại vương cứ tự nhiên
ask." "Regarding the sixth point, children under B
hỏi Vâng ở lơi điểm thứ Sáu trẻ dưới B
years old cannot attain enlightenment. I am very skeptical.
tuổi không thể Đắc quả Trẫm rất nghi ngờ
Why? Because children under B years old have
Tại sao vậy vì trẻ dưới B Tuổi tâm hồn
very pure souls, free from attachment to wrong views,
rất trong chắng chẳng ngã chấp tà kiến
without thoughts of lust, without cruelty, anger, envy, arrogance, or attachment to afflictions.
chẳng tư duy về ái dục chẳng độc ác sân
With such good qualities,
nung phiền não với nhân tố tốt đẹp như
if they diligently practice the Dharma,
vậy nếu trăm chuyên thực hành pháp Tại
why can't they attain enlightenment?" The Venerable Naxīna
sao lại không Đạt Đạo Đại Đức Na tiên
replied, "Your Majesty, with the normal strength
đáp đại vương với sức mạnh bình thường
of a human being, can one lift Mount Sumeru?" The
của con người có thể bưng được núi tu di
king replied, "Of course not."
không vua đáp hẳn nhiên là không
The Venerable Naxīna asked, "Why?" The
thể đại đức Na Tiên hỏi tại sao
king replied, "Mount Sumeru is too big, and human strength is
thế vua đáp tại núi tu Duy quá to mà sức
limited." The Venerable Lāxīna said, "It's the same, Your Majesty. The path to
hạn ngài la tiên nói cũng như thế đó tâu
enlightenment is a transcendental Dharma;
đại vương đạo quả là pháp xuất thế gian
it is too great, too sublime compared to the
nó quá vĩ đại quá cao siêu so với trí
normal intellect of a human being. Children under B
tuệ bình thường của con người trẻ dưới B
years old have weak bodies, their knowledge and thinking are
tuổi thể xác non yếu kiến thức và tư duy
not yet mature, their faith is not yet
đều chưa được chín chắn Đức Tin chưa
strong, and their intellect is too immature.
vững mạnh trí tuệ còn quá non nớt thì
How can they have the necessary conditions and abilities to
làm thế nào đủ điều kiện năng lực để
practice and deeply understand the great Dharma?"  "Yes, Your Majesty," the
thực hành và thâm ngộ đạo lớn được hở
king said. "Oh, that's quite possible," the king replied. The venerable
Ồ có thể là vậy lắm đức vua đáp đại đức
Na Tien continued with another example: "Can a single drop of
Na Tiên lại ví dụ tiếp ví như một giọt
water soak the entire earth?"
nước nhỏ có thể thấm ướt cả quả đất được
the king said. "Of course
chăng đại vương vua nói Dĩ nhiên là
not," the king replied. "Why?" Na Tien asked. The
không thể rồi đại đức Na Tiên hỏi tại
king answered, "Because the earth is too vast."
sao như thế vua đáp vì quả đất lớn quá
Na Tien said, "It's the same, Your
Đại Đức na-tiên nói cũng như thế đó đại
Majesty. Understand that the land of enlightenment is
vương hãy hiểu cho mảnh đất của đạo quả
also vast and boundless. All the knowledge, faith, and
cũng rộng lớn mênh mông Tất cả hiểu biết
wisdom of a child under seven years old are
Đức tin trí tuệ của trẻ dưới bả tuổi đều
tiny and insignificant. How can they possibly
nhỏ nhít tí tẹo thì làm sao có thể thâm
penetrate the realm of a sage?"
nhập cảnh Giới Của Thánh Nhân được hở
the king replied, "Yes."
Đại Vương Đức vua đáp thưa
Na Tien continued, "For example, if
Vâng ngài la Tiên lại nói lại nữa ví như
someone takes a small lamp and wants to
có người lấy cây đèn nhỏ mà muốn dọi
illuminate the entire kingdom, can they do
sáng cho thấy cả Quốc độ y có thể làm
that, Your Majesty?" The king said, "It's truly
thế được không đại vương vua nói thật
impossible." Na Tien asked, "Why?" The
không thể đại đức Na Tiên hỏi tại sao
king answered, "Because the light of the lamp is
vua đáp vì vùng chiếu sáng của ngọn đèn
only within a small limit, while the kingdom is
chỉ Trong một giới hạn nhỏ còn Quốc độ
too vast." Na Tien said, "It's the same; the
thì to lớn quá Đại Đức na-tiên nói cũng
immature wisdom of a child
như thế đó là trí tuệ non nớt của trẻ
under seven years old is compared to the enlightened world
dưới bả tuổi so với thế giới giác ngộ
of a sage." The
của bậc thánh
king replied, "Yes." Na Tien then
nhân vua đáp vâng đại đức na-tiên lại
asked again, "Why not?"  For example, imagine a type of worm that bores into rice
hỏi tiếp ví như có loại sâu chuyên đục
stalks.
thân núa s
Could that worm possibly eat a
ni con sâu ấy có thể nào ăn một con voi
four-foot-tall elephant? The
cao bốn thước không đại
king couldn't possibly do that. The king replied, "Venerable Na
vương chẳng thể nào vua đáp đại đức Na
Tien asked why." The king answered, "Because the worm's ability is
Tiên hỏi vì sao vua đáp vì khả năng con
incapable of doing that."
sâu không thể làm việc
Venerable Na Tien said, "It's the same; the
ấy đại đức Na tiên nói cũng như thế đó
combined abilities of a child under seven
là tổng cộng mọi năng lực của trẻ dưới B
years old are insufficient to achieve
tuổi nó không có khả năng thành tựu được
enlightenment." The king said, "Oh, Venerable
thánh đạo đâu đại vương vua nói cả Ơ đại
Na Tien has kindly explained." Respectfully, dear fellow practitioners, the following is merely Venerable Na Tien's explanation of the
giải thích của đại đức Na tiên cho cái
king's question about why children
thắc mắc của ông vua về tại sao lại trẻ
under seven years old cannot attain
dưới 7 tuổi lại không có thể Đắc được
enlightenment. Therefore, the purpose of this
thánh quả thôi Thế thì tâm chếu hoàn
sharing with you today is to
Quán hôm nay chia sẻ với quý đạo hữu là
instill faith
để cho chúng ta có lòng
in
tin lòng tin về chính
ourselves, faith in
mình lòng tin
our ability to attain
là mình có khả năng đắc
enlightenment, because we are outside the fifteen categories of beings that
đạo vì chúng ta nằm ngoài 15 cái loài
cannot attain
loại mà chúng sinh không thể đắc đạo cao
supreme enlightenment. Therefore, whether we are male
siêu cho nên chúng ta dù mang thân nữ
or female, as long as we are
hay dù mang thân Nam mà chúng ta nằm
outside
ngoài
these fifteen categories, we can attain enlightenment.
loại này thì chúng ta có thể đắc đạo
So, sometimes we are
được cho nên là nhiều lúc chúng ta phân
hesitant...  I'm sure I can't practice. I'm sure I ca
vân là tôi chắc không tu được đâu Tôi Tu
n't attain enlightenment. It's
chắc không đắc đạo được
very difficult to practice in this era, it's probably
đâu Thời này khó tu lắm chắc là cái thời
impossible to practice in this time.
này không tu được đâu những cái những
Those doubts are because we don't
cái băn khoăn đó là do chúng ta chưa
know clearly. But today, these things
biết rõ Thế còn hôm nay những điều này
help us to awaken, to liberate ourselves
giúp cho chúng ta giác ngộ ra chúng ta
from that hesitation, to
giải thoát khỏi cái sự ban khoan đó giải
liberate ourselves from self-doubt, that is, to liberate ourselves from doubt about whether
thoát khỏi cái sự nghi ngờ về chính mình
we can practice and attain enlightenment. Can we practice?
về chính mình là mình có thể tu được đắc
That is, today we are freed from
Tức là hôm nay chúng ta giải thoát được
that ignorance, we are enlightened, and
cái sự vô minh đó mà chúng
we can practice.
ta giác ngộ được ra rồi là chúng ta tu
We have pure faith in
được chúng ta có lòng tin thanh tịnh với
our karmic conditions for practice, right?
cái nhân duyên tu của mình phải không
If we just practice, we will attain enlightenment, it's not a problem. It's just
Nếu chúng ta cứ Tu là sẽ đắc đạo không
whether we
sao cả chỉ có cái là chúng ta
have pure faith in the Buddha
có có đức tin trong sạch với giáo pháp
's teachings or not, whether
của phật hay chưa thôi chúng ta có thể
we can diligently practice or not. All the other karmic conditions are within our
lại tất cả các nhân duyên là chúng ta có
control. The karmic conditions for attaining enlightenment are within
thể tu được nhân duyên để mà đắc đạo là
our control because
chúng ta có thể tu được bởi vì sự tinh
diligence is something we control
tấn là do chính mình mà mình làm chủ
ourselves. That's the faith we control.  Through practicing the Dharma,
cũng làm chủ được mình cứ thực hành pháp
we experience the benefits of the
mình cứ trải nghiệm được lợi ích của
Dharma, and our faith increases.
Pháp là lòng tin là tăng lên thôi Thế
Therefore, the more diligent we are, the
cho nên lòng càng tinh tấn bao nhiêu thì
purer and stronger our faith becomes. And that
cái lòng tin càng trong sạch bấy nhiêu
pure faith, in turn, fuels our diligence.
tin trong sạch đó lại khiến chúng ta
Diligence increases faith, and faith
tinh tấn cứ tinh tấn lại tăng trưởng
in turn
thêm lòng tin từ lòng tin lại tăng
increases diligence. Initially, we
trưởng sự tinh tấn thì mới đầu chúng ta
must have faith in cause and effect, and
phải có cái cái lòng tin về nhân quả
then we must diligently listen to the Buddha's teachings. This diligent
xong sau đó chúng ta phải chăm Nghe Phật
listening leads to
pháp thì cái chăm Nghe Phật pháp khiến
diligent practice, and through
chúng ta tinh tấn thực hành thế rồi
diligent practice, we
chúng ta tinh tấn thực hành thì chúng ta
gain the
lại được cái lợi
benefit of experiencing the truth, which further
ích trải nghiệm được sự thật lại tăng
increases our faith. Therefore, anyone with
trưởng đòng tin thế cho nên là ai mà
more than 10 years of this karmic connection
ngoài 10 năm cái nhân duyên này thì đều
can become diligent. So here,
có thể tinh tấn được nhé Thế thì ở đây
we are people who don't dare claim to be diligent,
Chúng ta là những người không dám nhận
but we dare
là mình đã tinh tấn nhưng mình cũng dám
acknowledge that we have tried, are
nhận rằng mình là người đã cố gắng đang
trying, and will continue to try. We will
cố gắng và sẽ cố gắng và chúng ta sẽ
encourage each other on
cùng nhau sách tấn nhau đi trên con
this path until we achieve liberation. I
đường này tới khi nào đạt được giải
respectfully request that all fellow practitioners, with the same
đấy kính mong các quý đạo hữu cùng với
mind as the Lord,
tâm Chúa Hoàn quán chúng ta cùng nhau
promise each other that we will be friends.  Let us
hứa với nhau là chúng ta sẽ là bạn hữu
practice together, let us walk
của nhau cùng nhau tu tập cùng nhau đi
this path together, because we
trên con đường này vì chúng ta là người
have the potential for cultivation. We have the potential for cultivation,
có cái căn tu nhá chúng ta có că tu cho
so let us walk
nên chúng ta sẽ cùng nhau đi trên con
this path together, my dear fellow practitioners. I wish you all diligence. Let
đường này nhé các quý đạo hữu nhé chúc
us all clasp our hands and dedicate
đạo hữu chúng ta chắp tay hồi hướng công
this merit, praying that all
này
beings, including the Fourth Buddha,
cả đệ
may choose to attain
sinh đều chọn Thành à
Buddhahood.
Phật đạo
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
K
K
Applause] [
[Vỗ tay]
Music]
[âm nhạc]